一个秋天的星期二早晨
One Tuesday morning in autumn
八点半整
at precisely half past eight,
歇洛克・福尔摩斯收到了一条神秘字条
Sherlock Holmes received a mysterious message
两位身世显赫的人
that two men of great public distinction
在完全保密的
would be visiting Baker's Street
情况下
in their private capacity
乘坐他们的私人马车
and under circumstances
正赶往贝克街
of complete secrecy.
第二块血迹
The Sencond Stain
福尔摩斯 他们到了
Holmes, they're here.
简短的说 福尔摩斯先生
In brief, Mr. Holmes.
一份文件
A document has been stolen
从我的私人公文箱中被偷了
from my private dispatch box
当我发现了失窃
and when I discovered my loss,
已是今天早晨八点
which was at eight o'clock this morning,
我立即报告了首相
I at once informed the Prime Minister.
根据他的建议
It was at his suggestion
我们俩来找你
that we both come to you.
你们已经报警了吗
You have informed the police?
没有先生 我们还没有那么做
No sir, we have not done so,
并且我们也不可能那样做
nor is it possible that we should do so.
从长远角度来看 让警方知道
To inform the police must, in the long run,
意味着公诸于众
mean to inform the public.
那是我们
And that is what we
极其要避免的
particularly desire to avoid.
为什么 先生
And why, sir?
因为那文件在一定程度上
Because the document in question
是如此的重要
is of such immense importance
以至于它的发表
that its publication might very easily,
我是说可能
I might almost say probably,
很容易导致
lead to European complications
欧洲的极度混乱
of the utmost moment.
追回文件一事
Unless its recovery is attended
必须绝对保密
by the utmost secrecy,
否则也就毫无必要
then it may as well not be recovered at all,
因为盗窃文件的目的
for all that is aimed at
正是为了
by those who have taken it
公布
is that its contents
文件的内容
should be generally known.
我明白了
I understand.
华生
Watson,
请坐下吧
do sit down.
现在 催罗尼・侯普先生
Now, Mr. Trelawney Hope,
如果您能告诉我
I'd be much obliged if you would tell me
这文件丢失时的确切情形
the exact circumstances
我将不胜感激
under which this document disappeared.
作为欧洲事务大臣
As Secretary of State for European affairs,
我在六天前收到了一封信
I received the letter six days ago.
它是一位外国君主寄来的
It was a letter from the foreign potentate
你知道的
you understand.
它非常重要
It was of such importance
我从不敢把它放在我的保险柜中
that I never left it in my safe,
而是每天从办公室
but I have taken each evening from my office,
带回到我在白厅住宅街的家中
back to my house in Whitehall Terrace,
并且把它放在我的卧室中
and kept it in my bedroom,
锁在文件箱里
locked in my dispatch box.
你确定昨晚它是在里面吗
And you are sure it was there last night?
是的 我很肯定
Yes, I'm quite certain of that fact.
实际上我打开了文件箱
I actually opened the dispatch box
在我晚饭前穿衣时
while I was dressing for dinner,
我看到文件在里面
and I saw the letter inside.
然后它一直在我旁边的桌子上
It then remained upon my bedside table.
我和我妻子睡觉都很轻
Both my wife and I are light sleepers
并且发誓肯定
and are prepared to swear that no one
那晚没人进入房间
could have entered the room during the night.
然而今早那文件却不见了
And yet this morning the paper is gone.
你什么时候吃的晚饭
What time did you dine?
七点半
Seven-thirty.
过了多长时间你去睡觉的
How long was it before you went to bed?
我妻子去看戏了
My wife had gone to the theatre.
我一直坐在外屋等她
I had waited up for her.
到十一点半我们才回屋睡觉
It was eleven-thirty before we went our room.
那么在四个小时中
So for four hours
文件箱是没人看管的?
the dispatch box had lain unguarded?
福尔摩斯先生 从没人被允许进那屋子
Mr. Holmes,no one is ever permitted to enter that room
除了女仆早晨去过
save the housemaid in the morning,
和我的仆人其他时间去过
and my valet during the rest of the day.
他们都是值得信任的仆人
They are both trusty servants
给我们工作了很多年
who have been with us for many years.
同时
Besides,
他们不可能知道
neither of them could have possibly known
在我的箱子中有比一般文件
that there was anything more valuable than the ordinary
都贵重的东西
departmental papers in my box.
确信你的妻子知道吗
Surely your wife knew?
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes?
我知道
I have long known how high
侯普先生有很强的社会责任感
Mr. Hope's sense of public duty.
我确信在这件重要的事中
I am convinced that in the case of this importance
信件的保密工作会重于
it would rise superior to the most
家庭感情
intimate domestic ties.
承蒙您过奖了 首相先生
You do me no more than justice, Prime Minister.
直到今早我都未向妻子
Until this morning I have never breathed one word
提起过这件事
to my wife upon this matter.
在英格兰
Who is there in England
谁还知道这封信的存在
who did know the existence of this letter?
昨天通知了各位内阁大臣
Each member of the Cabinet
有这样一封信
was informed of it yesterday
每天内阁会议都会
but the pledge of secrecy,
强调保密
which attends every Cabinet meeting,
特别是首相
was increased by the solemn warning
郑重地提醒了大家
given by the Prime Minister.
我的天啊
My God,
一想到几个小时中
to think that within a few hours
我就弄丢了它
I myself should have lost it.
除了内阁成员们
Besides the members of the Cabinet
还有两人
there are two,
可能有三个
possibly three,
官员
departmental officials
知道这信
who know of the letter.
我可以保证在英国再没其他人了
No one else in England, I assure you.
国外呢
But abroad?
我相信国外没人
I believe that no one abroad
看过这信
has seen the letter
除了写信的人
except the man who wrote it.
我深信写信的人
I am well convinced that his ministers
他没有通过一般官方的渠道
that the usual official channels
来处理这封信
have not been employed in this case.
现在 先生 我不得不问一下
Now, sir, I must ask you more particularly
那文件是关于什么的
what this document is,
而且它为什么
and why its disappearance
会引起严重的后果
should have such momentous consequences?
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes,
那信封薄而长
the envelope is a long, thin one
是浅灰色的
of pale blue color.
用红蜡封着
There's a seal of red wax
印有蹲着的狮子
stamped with a crouching lion.
收信人的地址是黑色的手写体
It is addressed in large, bold handwriting...
确实很有趣
Interesting and indeed
这些细节同样重要
essential as these details are,
我必须知道更根源的事情
my inquiries must go more to the root of things.
那是封怎样的信
What was the letter?
那是政府的最高机密
That is a State secret of the utmost importance,
我们不能告诉你
which we cannot tell you,
并且我看那也不必要
nor do I see that it is necessary.
如果能通过你的能力
If by the powers which you are said to possess
找到我描述的信
you can find such an envelope as I describe
连同它的附件
with its enclosure
你将得到国家的奖赏
then you will have deserved well of your country,
同时得到我们权限内
and earned any reward,
任何的报酬
which it is within our power to bestow.
先生们
Gentlemen,
你们是这个国家中
you are two of the most
最忙碌的两个人
busy men in the country
我这个小侦探也很忙
and in my own small way
有很多人来找我帮忙
I have a good many calls upon me.
很遗憾在这件事上
I regret exceedingly
我没办法帮你们
that I am unable to help you in this matter,
在目前的情形下
and any continuation of this interview
这次见面是在浪费时间
would be a waste of time.
从没人这样对我说话
I am not accustomed sir to such things.
亲爱的福尔摩斯先生
Dear Mr. Holmes,
我们必须得接受你的要求
we must accept your terms.
毫无疑问你是对的
No doubt you are right,
只有完全信任你
and it is unreasonable for us to expect you
你才能展开工作
to act unless you have our full confidence.
我同意你 首相先生
I agree with you, Prime Minister.
那么我将告诉你
Then I will tell you,
完全相信你
relying entirely upon your honor
和你的同事 华生先生的荣誉
and that of your colleague, Dr. Watson.
我也信任你们有强烈的爱国心
I must appeal to your patriotism also,
因为我不敢想象
for I cannot imagine
一旦事情暴露
a greater misfortune for this country
我们的国家将遭受多么大的灾难
than that this affair should come out.
您可以放心地信任我
You may safely trust us.
那封信
The letter, then,
来自一位外国君主
is from a certain foreign potentate
他对我国殖民地的迅速发展
who has been ruffled by some recent
感到愤慨从而写了这封信
colonial developments of this country.
信是匆匆写成的
It is written hurriedly
且完全出于他个人的意见
and upon his own responsibility entirely.
于此同时
At the same time
这封信写得很不合体统
it is couched in so unfortunate a manner
它的发表无疑
that its publication would undoubtedly
会激怒英国人
lead to the most dangerous feeling in this country.
它会引起轩然大波
There would be such ferment, sir
我敢说
that I do not hesitate to say
这封信如果发表
that within a week
在一个星期内
of the publication of this letter
这个国家将卷进战争中
this country would be involved in a great war.
正是这封信
And it is this letter,
将意味着花费
which may well mean the expenditure
几亿英镑
of a thousand million pounds
和几十万
and the lives
人民的牺牲
of a hundred thousand men.
你通知写信的人了吗
Have you informed the sender?
已经发了密码电报
A cipher telegraph has been dispatched.
或许他希望信被发表
Perhaps he desires the publication of the letter.
不 医生 我们有足够的理由相信
No, Doctor, we have strong reason to believe
他已经感到了
that he already understands that he has
自己的急躁与不谨慎
acted in an indiscreet and hotheaded manner.
如果信被发表
It would be a far greater blow to him
对他自己国家的打击
and his country than to us
比对英国的大得多
if this letter were to come out.
如果这样的话
If this is so,
公布这信将符合哪些人的利益呢
in who's interest is it that the letter should come out?
为什么有人会盗窃并发表这封信呢
Why should anyone desire to steal it or publish it?
那样的话 华生医生
There, Doctor Watson, you take me into the realms
就牵扯到紧张的国际关系了
of high international politics.
如果你考虑一下目前欧洲的情况
But if you consider the European situation
就不难看出
you will have no difficulty
其中真正的动机
in perceiving the motive.
整个欧洲是个武装起来的堡垒
The whole of Europe is an armed camp.
大不列颠保持中立
Great Britain holds the scales.
如果英国被迫
If Britain were driven into war
与哪个联盟交战
with one confederacy,
必定会使另一个联盟获利
it would assure the supremacy of the other,
无论它们是否参与战争
whether they were joined in the war or not.
那么是否是这位君主的敌人
So does the enemies of this potentate
想要得到并发表这封信
who want to secure and publish this letter,
来分裂
so as to make a breach
他的国家和我国
between his country and ours?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
如果这信落入敌人手中
And to whom would the document be sent
他将把它交给谁呢
if it fell into the wrong hands?
给欧洲任何一个国家的一个大臣
To any of the great chancelleries of Europe.
或许目前持信的人
It is probably speeding its way thither
正乘火车
at the present instant
火速前往目的地
as fast as steam can take it.
亲爱的朋友 那是你的不幸
It is your misfortune, my dear fellow.
谁都不能责怪你
No one can blame you.
你没有疏忽大意
There's no precaution which you have neglected.
但是现在 福尔摩斯先生
But now, Mr. Holmes,
事情你全了解了
you are in full possession of the facts.
你认为该怎么办
What course do you recommend?
你认为找不到这封信
You think that if this document is not recovered
会发生战争吗
there will be war?
我觉得很有可能
I think it is very probable.
那么 先生 请准备打仗吧
Then, sir, prepare for war.
福尔摩斯先生 很难说找不回来了
That is a hard saying, Mr. Holmes.
考虑现实情况
Consider the facts.
可以想象那文件
It seems no doubt this document was taken
在七点半到十一点半之间
between half past seven
已被拿走
and half past eleven yesterday evening,
那么它现在会在哪呢
so where can it be now?
谁也没有理由扣押这封信
No one has any reason to retain it.
它已很快地被
It has been passed from hand to hand rapidly
交到需要它的人手中
to those who need it
或以高价买它的人手中
and who will pay well for it.
我们能有什么机会
What chance do we have
找到它或弄清它在哪
to overtake it or even trace it?
这超出我的能力范围
It is beyond our reach.
福尔摩斯先生 你说的完全符合逻辑
What you say is perfectly logical, Mr. Holmes.
我感到我们确实无能为力
I feel that the matter is indeed out of our hands.
同时 侯普
Meanwhile, Hope,
我们不要因为这件不幸的事
we cannot ignore all our other duties
而忽略了其他职责
on account of this one misfortune.
今天如果有新的进展
Should there be any fresh developments
我们会告诉你
during the day we will communicate with you
你也务必让我们了解
and you no doubt will let us know
你调查的结果
the results of your own inquiries.
谢谢
Thank you.
报纸
Telegraph!
维斯特敏斯特谋杀案
Westminster Murder!
报纸
Telegraph!
维斯特敏斯特谋杀案
Westminster Murder!
报纸
Telegraph!
情形令人绝望
The situation is desperate,
但不是完全没有希望
but not hopeless.
只有三个人
There are only three men
敢冒这么大危险
capable of playing so bold a game
奥波尔斯坦 拉若泽和艾秋阿多・卢卡斯
Oberstein, La Rothiere, and Eduardo Lucas.
甚至是现在 如果我们知道
Even now, if we could be sure
是谁拿了信
which one of them has taken it,
有可能的话
it is just possible
他们还没有把信出手
that it has not passed out of their hands.
这只是钱的问题
It's a question of money with these fellows,
不是吗
isn't it?
我们有英国财政部的支持
Well we have the British Treasure behind us.
如果他肯出价 我就会买下它
Oh if it's on the market I'll buy it
不管花多少钱
if it means another penny on the income tax.
请进
Come in.
打扰你了 福尔摩斯先生
Excuse, Mr. Holmes.
哈德森太太 有什么事
Mrs. Hudson, what is it?
希尔达・崔洛尼・侯普小姐
Lady Hilda Trelawney Hope,
请她进来
show her in.
福尔摩斯先生 我丈夫来过这儿吗
Has my husband been here, Mr. Holmes?
是的 女士 他来过
Madam, yes he has been here.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes,
我请求您
I implore you
不要告诉他我来过
not to tell him I came here.
夫人
Your ladyship puts me
您令我很为难
in a very delicate position.
请您坐下
I beg of you to sit down
并告诉我您有什么请求
and tell me what it is you desire
但我不能无条件地答应您一切
but I cannot make you any unconditional promise.
先生 我将对您开诚布公
Gentlemen, I will speak frankly to you
同时期望那将
in the hope that it will induce you
使您对我也能坦率
to speak frankly in return.
我和我丈夫在任何事情上
There is complete confidence
都完全地互相信任
between my husband and myself
除了一件事
on all matters except one.
那就是政治问题
That one is politics.
在这方面他总是守口如瓶
On this his lips are sealed.
他从不告诉我任何事
He tells me nothing.
现在我知道了
Now, I am aware that there was a most
昨晚我们家发生了一件很不幸的事
deplorable occurrence in our house last night.
我知道一份文件丢失了
I know that a paper has disappeared.
但是事关政治
But because the matter is political
我丈夫并没有
my husband refuses to take me
对我完全讲清楚
into his complete confidence.
这事情非常重要
Now it is essential
非常重要
essential, I say
我应该彻底了解这件事
that I should thoroughly understand it.
除了几位政治家之外
You are the only people,
您是唯一
save these politicians,
了解情况的人
who know the true facts,
至少我推测是这样
at least I presume you do.
你推测得没错 夫人
You presume correctly, madam.
我请求您
I beg you then,
告诉我发生了什么
tell me exactly what has happened
可能会导致什么结果
and what it may lead to.
请详细告诉我 福尔摩斯先生
Tell me all, Mr. Holmes.
不要因为怕损失我丈夫的利益
Let no regard for my husband's interest
而不肯告诉我
keep you silent,
我向您保证
for I assure you
他早晚会明白
that his interests,
因为只有完全相信我
if he would only see it,
他的利益
would be best served by taking me
才能有所保证
into his complete confidence.
是什么文件被偷了
What was this paper, which was stolen?
夫人 您所问的是不能说的
Madam, what you ask me is really impossible.
你要明白我只能这么做
You must see that this so.
您丈夫认为不该让您
If your husband thinks fit
知道这件事
to keep you in the dark over this matter,
那么我
is it for me,
由于职业的缘故
who has only learned the true facts
才知道的全部真相
under the pledge of professional secrecy,
能随便说出来吗
to tell what he has withheld?
不应该问起的
It is not fair to ask it.
你必须问他本人
It is he who you must ask.
我问过他了
I have asked him.
我是万不得已才来问您的
I come to you as a last resort.
您既然不肯告诉我
But without your telling me anything definite
能不能帮我一个忙
you may do me a great service
给我一点启发
if you would enlighten me on one point.
启发是指什么 夫人
What is it, madam?
我丈夫的政治生涯是否会
Is my husband's political career
因为这件事受到影响
likely to suffer through this incident?
除非事情处理得当
Well let me say if it is not put right
否则后果非常严重
it may have a very unfortunate effect.
这样
Oh.
还有一个问题 福尔摩斯先生
One more question, Mr. Holmes.
从我丈夫对此事
From an expression which my husband dropped
一显出惊奇开始
in the first shock of the disaster
我就明白因为文件的丢失
I understood that terrible public consequences
会在社会上引起一系列影响
might arise from the loss this document.
如果他这么说 我不能否定
If he said so, I cannot deny it.
后果会是什么性质的
Of what nature are they?
又来了
There again
您所问的
you ask me more
我不能回答
than I can possibly answer.
那我就不耽误您的时间了
Then I will waste no more of your time.
福尔摩斯先生 我不怪您
I cannot blame you, Mr. Holmes,
讲话过于严谨
for refusing to speak more freely,
而我相信您不会
and you on your side will not,
说我的不好
I am sure, think the worst of me
因为我希望分担他的忧虑
because I desire to share my husband's anxieties,
即使违背他的意愿
even against his will.
再一次请求您
Once more I beg
不要告诉他我来过
you will say nothing of my visit.
我要说
I say,
一位多么出众
what a really remarkable
而美丽的女士啊
and beautiful woman.
女性属于你的研究范围 华生
The fair sex is your department, Watson.
她的真正意图是什么
What did she really want?
意图她讲得很清楚
Surely her own statement was clear
她的焦虑也很自然
and her anxiety very natural.
想想她的表情 华生 她的举止
Think of her appearance, Watson, her manner,
她压抑着的焦虑
her suppressed excitement,
她的不安
her restlessness,
一再提出的问题
her tenacity in asking questions.
别忘了她是贝尔敏斯特伯爵的
Remember she is the youngest daughter
小女儿
of the Duke of Belminster
出身于一个
and comes of a cast
不会轻易表露感情的阶层
that does not likely show emotion.
她心里其实很激动
She was certainly much moved.
你当然观察到了
And you observed, of course,
她总是设法背对着阳光
how she maneuvered to have her back to the light.
她不希望我们看清楚
She did not wish us
她的面目表情
to read her expression too closely.
是的 她特意选择了那个椅子
Yes; she choose that chair in the whole room.
女性的心理活动很难猜测
And yet the motives of women are so inscrutable.
你怎能这样轻信呢
I mean, how could build on such a quicksand?
有时她们一个细小的举动包含重大意义
Their most trivial action may mean volumes,
一个发针或一把卷发火剪
or their most extraordinary conduct
就可以显露出她们的反常
may depend upon a hairpin or a curling tong.
早上好 华生
Good morning, Watson.
你要出去
You off then?
是啊
Yes.
福尔摩斯
Holmes?
是不是那三个嫌犯之一
Was one of the agents you spoke of
有个叫艾秋阿多・卢卡斯的
called Eduardo Lucas?
是的
Yes.
高道尔芬街的?
Of Godolphin Street?
是啊
Yes.
你不能去见他了
You'll not see him.
为什么
Why not?
他昨晚在家被谋杀了
He was murdered in his house last night.
说是谋杀吗
Does it say murdered?
在维斯特敏斯特被谋杀的
Murdered in Westminster.
一位神秘人的罪行
Crime of a mysterious character.
艾秋阿多・卢卡斯
Eduardo Lucas,
未婚 34岁
unmarried, thirty-four,
因为他的人格魅力
well known in society circles
在社会圈子里很有名
on account of his charming personality.
仆人们晚上不在家      总是这样
Valet out for the evening.        They always are.
上年纪的管家
Elderly housekeeper
睡在房子顶层 什么也没听到
sleeps at the top of the house, heard nothing.
他们永远听不到
They never do.
午夜前
Just before midnight
警察巴瑞特巡逻路过时
police constable, Barrett,
看到门半开着
saw a door ajar,
看到卢卡斯被刀子扎中了心脏
Found Lucas stabbed to the heart.
让我看看
Awe, let me see.
普鲁士匕首
Prussian dagger.
动机不像是抢劫
Robbery does not appear to be the motive.
贵重物品没有被动过
Valuable collection untouched.
你认为是怎么回事 华生
What do you make of this, Watson?
是个...
Well it's an...
是个惊人的巧合
it's an amazing coincidence.
巧合
Coincidence?
他就是我们刚说过的
Here is one of the three men
三个人中最可能
whom we have named
登台表演的人
as possible actors in this drama,
正在这场戏
and he meets a violent end
上演的时候
during the very hours we know
他惨死了
that drama is enacted.
从情况看多半
The odds are enormously
不是巧合
against it being a coincidence.
两件事有联系
The two events are connected
一定有联系
must be connected.
我们正是要找出之间的联系
It is for us to find the connection.
现在警察一定全知道了
By now the police must know all.
不 还没有
No, not at all.
他们只知道在高德尔芬街看到的
They know all they see at Godolphin Street.
他们肯定不知道
They know, and shall know nothing
白厅住宅街的事
of Whitehall Terrace.
只有我们全知道
Only we know of both events,
并可以弄清两者之间的关系
and can trace the relation between them.
我们的问题
It is with the late Eduardo Lucas
和艾秋阿多・卢卡斯有直接关系
that the solution to our problem lies.
事情还没发生就得出结论
But it is a capital mistake
这是个极大的错误
to theorize in advance of the facts.
你值班接待客人 我的好华生
You stay here my good, Watson,
我尽量回来和你一起吃饭
I will join you when I'm able.
华生 他们逮捕了仆人
Watson, they've arrested the valet.
雷斯垂德负责这个案子
Lestrade has been put in charge of the case.
他像个苍蝇一样到处嗡嗡
He's buzzing around like a blue bottle.
我应该认识到这点
I've got to know him rather well.
如果我去和他谈会有帮助吗
Would it help if I spoke to him?
不 不会有帮助
No, no it would not.
这个案子
This is a case where
警察对我们来说和对罪犯
the law is as dangerous to us
一样危险
as the criminals are.
我们必须耐心等待
We must be patient and wait.
卢卡斯谋杀案
Lucas murder case.
《标准晚报》
The Evening Standard.
卢卡斯谋杀案
Lucas murder case.
嫌疑人被释放
Suspect released.
谋杀案
Murder case.
嫌疑人被释放
Suspect released.
《标准晚报》
The Evening Standard.
卢卡斯谋杀案
Lucas murder case.
早餐 福尔摩斯先生
Breakfast, Mr. Holmes.
不 不 不 谢谢 哈德森太太
No, no, No thank you, Mrs. Hudson.
我不想吃
I don't want any.
我不知道怎么说 你再这样下去会晕倒的
I don't know. You'll fade away at this rate.
福尔摩斯 他们找到凶手了
I say, Holmes, they've found the murderer
或者说是女凶手
or rather the murderess.
是的
Indeed.
有条巴黎来的线索
There's a wire from Paris.
很明显卢卡斯有着双重身份
Apparently Lucas was leading a double life.
他在法国有个太太是克里奥尔人
He had a Creole wife in France
他在那里自称亨利・弗那依
where he called himself Henri Fournaye.
他的几名仆人
The woman was reported to the police yesterday
向警察报告
by her servants,
说她已经精神失常
she is quite insane,
患有危险的长期狂躁症      可怜的女人
a mania of a dangerous and permanent form.        Poor woman
听这个
But listen to this.
一名容貌酷似她的妇女在
The same woman was seen
谋杀当晚在高德尔芬街
in the neighborhood of Godolphin Street
被人看到过
on the night of the murder
之后又在查林十字车站
and later made an emotional scene
因举止狂暴被人注意到
at Charing Cross Station.
你怎么看
Now what do you think of that?
我亲爱的华生
Oh my dear Watson,
你真能忍啊
you are so long-suffering,
过去几天我什么都没给你讲
if I've told you nothing over these last few days
因为没什么可说的
it is because there is nothing to tell.
现在从巴黎来的这个消息
Even now this report from Paris
同样没什么帮助
doesn't help us much.
和卢卡斯的死总还有关系吧
Well surely it's final as regards to Lucas' death.
他的死只是个意外
The man's death is a mere incident
和我们的真正目标
a trivial episode
寻找丢失文件
in comparison with our real task,
避免欧洲的一场灾难相比
which is to trace the document
只是小事一件
and save a European catastrophe.
如果这封信丢失了
Now if the letter were loose
不 不可能丢失
no, it cannot be loose
如果没丢
but if it isn't loose,
信又在哪呢
where can it be?
谁拿着这封信呢
Who has it?
为什么要扣押这封信呢
Why is it held back?
如果雷斯垂德在卢卡斯的文件中找到了信
Look if Lestrade found it amongst Lucas' papers
他不会傻到向公众公开
he's not such a fool as to announce it.
他会通报局长
He would inform the chief commissioner.
局长
The chief commissioner
会通报给内政大臣
would inform the Home Secretary
内政大臣最后会告诉首相
and he, in turn, the Prime Minister.
不 不是在卢卡斯的文件中
No it's not among Lucas' papers.
但为什么被扣押了呢
But why is it held back?
这才是问题所在
That is the question
像是一把锤头敲击着我的脑袋
which beats in my brain like a hammer.
卢卡斯被杀
Was it a mere coincidence
正是信丢失的那晚
that Lucas should meet his death
不会是巧合吗
on the night when the letter disappeared?
他拿到信了吗
Did it ever reach him?
她那位疯太太会不会
Has this mad wife of his
带着信回了巴黎
taken it with her to Paris?
如果是这样 会不会是在她巴黎的家里
If so, is it in her house in Paris?
要我去巴黎吗
Shall I go to Paris?
那会惊动巴黎警方的
That would alert the French Police.
人人都在和我们作对
Every man's hand is against us,
而偏偏
and yet,
事情又很重大
the interest at stake are colossal.
如果我能顺利解决这个案子
Should I bring this to a successful conclusion,
那无疑将是
it will certainly represent
我事业生涯最大的光荣
the crowning glory of my career.
福尔摩斯 小心
Holmes, look!
谢谢
Thank you.
给您 长官
There you go gov.
谢谢
Thank you.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes.
华生医生
Doctor Watson!
你们毫无疑问也在调查卢卡斯的案子吧?
You've no doubt been following the Lucas case?
卢卡斯
Lucas?
是啊 名字倒是挺熟悉的
Awe yes, the name does seem familiar to me.
艾秋阿多・卢卡斯
Eduardo Lucas
被发现上周二晚
found murdered last Tuesday night
在高德尔芬的家中被谋杀
at his house in Godolphin Street.
一位不同寻常的先生
Rather a distinguished gentlemen.
国际政治学学生
Student of international politics
有名的语言学家 他们是这样说的
and a remarkable linguist, so they say.
实际上是我负责这个案子
I've been in charge of the case, matter of fact.
不是个轻松的案子
Not an easy task by any means.
有一些很棘手的问题
Some delicate problems you understand?
但在法国同仁的帮助下
But to the aid of our French friends
我会令人满意地
I will be able to bring the case
解决这个案子
to a satisfactory conclusion.
所有线索又联系了起来
All the loose ends tied up.
我们弄清楚了
Oh we've got it,
就像亲眼看到一样
clear as if we'd seen it.
恭喜你 雷斯垂德
Congratulations, Lestrade.
你事业上又一笔功绩
Another feather in your cap.
谢谢
Thank you.
是的
Yes indeed.
你走之前 福尔摩斯先生
Oh before you go, Mr. Holmes,
有一件小事
it's a mere trifle,
但是你感兴趣的那类
but the sort of thing you take an interest in
怪事
queer, you know,
你可能称之为诡异
what you might call freakish.
和主要事实没有关系
It has nothing to do with the main fact,
必须亲眼看到才行
can't have, on the face of it.
是什么事
What is it, then?
如果你们
Well if you gentlemen
愿意来高德尔芬街一下
could come down to Godolphin Street
我想在现场解释
I think I could explain it
会比较清楚
better on the spot.
可能就几分钟吧
For a few minutes perhaps.
太好了 就在拐角那里
Oh good, it's only just around the corner.
谢谢你 车夫
Thank you Cabbie,
不用找钱了
keep the change.
就是这里
Here it all is.
那个女人看到仆人走了之后
Now the woman must have knocked on the door
她去敲了门
after she saw the valet had gone out.
毫无疑问是出乎意料的拜访
Surprise visit no doubt.
卢卡斯让她进来
Lucas let her in.
他不能让自己的妻子
He couldn't keep her on the street could he,
留在街上 不是吗
his own wife?
她用法语冲他大喊大叫
She started screaming at him being French.
借过
Excuse me.
说她如何跟踪他
Saying how'd she traced him
然后训斥他等等
and reproaching him and so on.
他们来到这里
Anyway they came in here
事情总是互相影响
and one thing led to another
匕首就在手边
and with the daggers being so handy
最后的事情发生了
the end came soon.
并不是立即死亡的
It didn't happen in an instant though
椅子全倒在墙边
for these chairs were swept over to the wall
他手里还抓着一把
and he had this one in his hand,
似乎他想用椅子挡开匕首
as if he did try to hold her off with it.
是的 雷斯垂德 谢谢
Yes Lestrade, thank you.
告诉我有什么怪事
Now tell me about this trifle.
你知道这类犯罪
Well, you know in crimes of this sort
我们会保持现场原状
we keep things in their position.
不准动任何东西
Nothing has moved.
派人日夜看守
Officers in charge day and night.
我很主意这点的
I'm always very particular on that point.
是的
Oh yes,
你的调查总是严谨细微 警探
you're meticulous in your investigations, Inspector.
今早 我们想
Well this morning we thought
应该可以收拾一下了
we could tidy up a bit.
尸检进行完了
Post-mortem over,
证据搜集完了
all the evidence gathered,
调查结束了
investigation complete,
但是 这块地毯
however, this carpet.
它并没有固定在地板上
As you can see it's not been fastened down,
只是摆在那里
it's just been laid there.
我们碰巧掀了一下地毯
Now we had occasion to raise it.
发现...
And we found...
什么
Yes?
你一百年也猜不出来
You'll never guess in a hundred years
我们发现了什么 福尔摩斯先生
what we did find, Mr. Holmes.
你看见这块血迹了吗
Now you see this stain?
大部分的血迹已经浸透了地毯
Now a good deal of blood must have soaked through,
是吧
must it not?
毫无疑问 是的
Undoubtedly it must.
你们听到我说在背面相应的地板上
Then you'll be surprised to hear
却没有血迹
that there is no stain on the woodwork
一定感到奇怪吧
to correspond.
没有血迹?
No stain?
可这绝对不可能啊
But there must be.
尽管你说一定有
So you would say.
事实上
Fact remains
没有
there isn't.
地毯上面和下面有同样的血迹
But the under side is as stained as the upper.
一定会留下痕迹的
It must have left a mark.
我来解开谜底
Now I will show you the explanation.
有第二块血迹
There is a second stain,
但是和第一块位置不一样
but it does not correspond with this one.
华生医生
Doctor Watson,
你能拿起地毯的另一边吗
will you take that side of the carpet?
我们转过来
Now we will move round
按照顺时针方向
in an empty clockwise direction.
我想知道 福尔摩斯先生
What I want to know is, Mr. Holmes,
是谁转动了地毯
who shifted the carpet
以及转动它的原因
and why?
雷斯垂德 谋杀第二天
Lestrade, who was on duty
这里谁负责看守
the day after the murder?
第二天?
The day after?
麦克弗逊
MacPherson.
他就在外面
He's out there now.
听我的
Take my advice.
好好审问他
Examine him carefully.
我会的
I'll get him.
别当着我们的面问
Don't do it before us.
我们在这里等
We'll wait here.
告诉他你知道有人进来过
Tell him you know someone has been here.
给他施压
Press him.
告诉他只有坦白
Tell him a full confession
才能绕他不死
is his only chance of forgiveness.
找我说的做
Do exactly as I tell you.
天啊 如果他知道什么
By George, if he knows
我一定要问出来
I'll have it out of him.
华生 去望风
Watson, quick get the table!
空的
Empty.
福尔摩斯
Holmes!
这里 警官
In here, Constable.
麦克弗逊
MacPherson.
家里人怎么样
How's the family?
很好 谢谢 先生
Very well, thank you sir.
好了 快说吧
Well come out with it.
让先生们听听
Let these gentlemen
你不可饶恕的罪行
hear of your inexcusable conduct.
我无疑冒犯 先生
Well I meant no harm sir, I'm sure.
一位年轻女士来到门前
This young woman came to the door
来应聘一个打字员的广告
answering an advertisement about typewriting.
她说找错房子了
It was mistook, the house she said.
正当我们说话时 先生 你知道的
While we were talking, sir, you know how it is?
一个人在外面看守一天
It's a bit lonely when you're out there
难免有些寂寞
on duty all day.
发生了什么 麦克弗逊
What happened, MacPherson?
先生 我们说到了这场谋杀
Well, sir, we got talking about the crime.
她说她在报纸上读到了
She had read about it in the paper, she said,
想看看案发现场
and wanted to see where it was done.
我觉得让她看看
So I saw no harm
没什么大碍
in letting her have a weak peep.
她走到大概门那个位置
She got just about in the door there,
看到了地毯上的血迹
spotted that mark in the carpet
然后晕倒在地板上
and down she dropped on the floor,
跟死了一样
and lay for dead.
难怪啊
And no wonder.
继续 麦克弗逊
Go on, MacPherson.
我就到拐角的常春藤商店
Well sir, I was away around at the lvy Plant
买了点白兰地 等我拿酒回来的时候
for some brandy, and by the time I had brought it back
那位年轻女士...
the young woman had...
已经不见了
well she wasn't here anymore.
肯定是她醒了过来自己离开了
She had recovered and was off.
她感到不好意思
Ashamed of herself,
不愿意再见我
and dared not face me.
麦克弗逊
MacPherson,
你动过地毯吗
did you move the carpet?
我只是把地毯摆好了
No sir, I only straightened it out.
她倒在地毯上了
You see she had fell on it
而地板又光又滑
and the polished floor being slippery.
记住这个教训 警官
Let that be a lesson to you, Constable,
你骗不了我
that you can't deceive me.
你一定以为你的失职
No doubt that you thought your breach of duty
不会被发现
would never be discovered,
可我一看地毯
and yet a mere glance at that carpet
就马上知道
was enough to convince me
有人到屋子里来过
that someone had been admitted to this room.
这是你的运气
Lucky for you, my man,
没丢什么东西
that nothing's missing.
不然你少不了吃苦头的
Otherwise you would find yourself in Queer Street.
就这样吧
That will do.
华生 我们还在这儿干什么
Watson, what are we doing here?
我们在别的地方还有事呢
We have work elsewhere.
你事业上又一笔功绩 雷斯垂德
Another feather in your cap, Lestrade.
谢谢 福尔摩斯先生
Oh thank you, Mr. Holmes.
上帝啊 福尔摩斯先生
Good Lord, Mr. Holmes!
嗨
Hey.
解决了吗
Have you solved it?
快了 华生 就快了
Hardly, Watson, hardly.
有两位先生想见您 小姐
Two gentlemen wish to speak to you, my lady.
他们没有预约
They do not have an appointment.
他们是谁 贝茨
Who are they, Bates?
歇洛克・福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Sherlock Holmes
还有华生医生 小姐
and a Doctor Watson, my lady.
很好
Very well.
带他们进来
You may show them in.
是的 小姐
Very well, my lady.
对不起
Excuse me.
福尔摩斯先生和华生医生 小姐
Mr. Holmes and Doctor Watson, my lady.
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes.
你实在太不公平
This is surely most unfair
太不宽厚了
and ungenerous on your part.
我解释过了 我希望
I have desired, as I have explained,
我去找你的事要保密
to keep my visit to you a secret
可你却到这里来
and yet you compromise me by coming here,
借此表明你和我
and so showing that there are
有事务联系
business relations between us.
不幸地是 夫人
Unfortunately, madam,
我没有别的选择
I have no possible alternative.
我受托找回这件
I've been commissioned to recover
极其重要的文件
an immensely important document.
只能请求您
I must ask you, therefore,
能好心
to be kind enough
把它交给我
to place it in my hands.
你这是在侮辱我 福尔摩斯先生
You insult me, Mr. Holmes.
不必摇铃 希尔达夫人
Do not ring, Lady Hilda.
如果你合作 我会安排好一切的
If you work with me I can arrange everything.
如果不合作
If you work against me,
我就要揭发你
I must expose you.
你想要吓唬我
You're trying to frighten me.
来到这里威胁一位女性
It's not a very manly thing, Mr. Holmes,
这可不是大丈夫的行为
to come here and browbeat a woman.
你说你了解了一些情况
You say you have something to tell me.
很好 我给你五分钟
Very well, I give you five minutes.
一分钟就够了 希尔达夫人
One is enough, Lady Hilda.
我知道你去过艾秋阿多・卢卡斯那里
I know of your visit to Eduardo Lucas,
你给了他这封信
of your giving him this letter,
知道你又巧妙地去过那间房子
of your ingenious return to the room
就在谋杀后第二天
on the evening after the murder,
还知道你怎么样从地毯下面
and of the manner in which you took this letter
隐蔽的地方取走了这封信
from it's hiding place under the carpet.
我一直带着这个
I have kept this because
因为我想也许有用
I thought it might be useful.
那个警察认出了你
The policeman recognized you.
再说一次 福尔摩斯先生
Once again, Mr. Holmes,
我告诉你 你疯了
I tell you you're under some absurd illusion.
很抱歉 希尔达女士
Oh I am so sorry, Lady Hilda.
我尽力了
I have done my best,
但我感觉都白费了
but I feel that I'm in vain.
崔洛・尼侯普先生在家吗
Is Mr. Trelawney Hope at home?
他十二点半回来 先生
He'll be back at half past twelve, sir.
还有一刻钟
Then we have a quarter of an hour.
我们就在这里等他
We will wait here.
饶恕我吧 福尔摩斯先生
Oh, spare me, Mr. Holmes.
饶了我吧
Spare me.
看在上帝的份上 别告诉他
For heaven's sake don't tell him.
我是那么爱他
I love him so.
我不愿意给他的生活带来不快
I would not bring one shadow on his life,
我知道这会让他伤透了心的
and this I know would break his noble heart.
我们时间紧迫啊
We have not an instant to lose.
信在哪里
Where is the letter?
在这儿
Here it is.
我发誓我没看过
I wish to heaven I'd never seen it.
文件箱呢?
And the dispatch box?
在我丈夫那
With my husband.
他总是随身携带的
Wherever he goes he takes it with him.
我们只有几分钟了
We only have a few minutes left.
希尔达夫人 我费了很大力气保护你
Now, Lady Hilda, I'm going far to screen you.
反过来
In return
你得坦白地告诉我
you will spend the time
你干这些不同寻常的事的
telling me frankly the real meaning
真正目的
of this extraordinary affair.
那天下午
It was on the afternoon of that day,
可怕的一天
that terrible day.
艾秋阿多卢卡被杀的那天?
The day Eduardo Lucas was murdered?
是的
Yes.
我正准备出去应酬
I was just going out to pay some calls
一封机密的信寄来给我
when a confidential note arrived for me.
是卢卡斯寄来的
It was from Lucas
让我立即去见他
asking me to visit him urgently,
他有一些重要并私密的事情
as he had important and private information
只能对我讲
for my ears alone.
他通过某种手段
He had obtained, in some way,
弄到了我的一封信
a letter of mine,
福尔摩斯先生
Mr. Holmes.
是在我婚前写的
An indiscreet letter
一封不慎重的信
written before my marriage.
愚蠢的信
Foolish letter.
一封感情冲动陷入恋爱的女孩子写的信
Letter of an impulsive, loving girl.
我没有恶意
I meant no harm,
可是我丈夫会认为这是犯罪
yet my husband would have thought it criminal.
要是他读了这封信
Had he read that letter
他便再也不会信任我了
his confidence would have been forever destroyed.
是很多年前写的了
It's years since I wrote it.
我以为这件事就这样过去了
I thought the whole matter was forgotten.
毫无疑问你写得很好
No doubt you remember to content very well.
很轻薄 我得说很轻薄
Very sprightly, I must say, very sprightly.
你的回答很漂亮
You make a charming correspondent.
你想从我得这里到什么 卢卡斯先生
What do you want with me, Mr. Lucas?
我能要回我的信吗
May I have my letter back please?
当然 希尔达夫人
Of course you may, Lady Hilda.
但这张纸可是很值钱的
But this is a very valuable piece of paper,
你不这么想吗
would you not agree?
我确定如果把它放在你丈夫面前
I'm sure if it was laid before your husband
他可不会喜欢这些内容的
he would hardly fail to appreciate the content.
你是个敲诈犯
You're a blackmailer.
是一位商人 希尔达夫人
A businessman, Lady Hilda.
这对我来说只是一笔交易
This is purely a business transaction on my side.
我保证我不希望看到
I can assure you I wish no ill
你和你丈夫不和
to you or your husband.
你想要多少钱
How much money do you want for that letter,
卢卡斯先生
Mr. Lucas?
不要提钱 夫人
Let's not speak of money, madam.
我的生意没那么简单
My business is not so simple as that.
钱很容易弄到
Well the matter is an easy one.
每晚
Every evening
当你丈夫从部里回来的时候
when your husband returns from his ministry
他都会带着
he brings with him
他的私人文件箱
his private dispatch box.
是不是这样
Is that not so?
是的
Yes.
他今晚回家时
When he comes home tonight
箱子里会有一封
this box will contain
长的蓝色的信
a long, blue envelope
用红蜡封着
sealed in red wax
上面是一只蹲着的狮子
with a crouching lion stamped on it.
把那封蓝信带给我
Bring me that long, blue envelope
连皮带瓤
with its contents
我就会还给你这个
and I will return you this.
可是我丈夫呢
But my husband?
他不会受到伤害的
No harm will come to him.
我向你保证
I can assure you.
换到我的立场想想
Put yourselves in my position.
我该做什么
What was I to do?
选择丈夫的信任
Take your husband into your confidence.
我不能 华生医生 我不能
I could not, Doctor Watson, I could not.
一方面会导致幸福的毁灭
On the one side seemed certain ruin
另一方面是件可怕的事
on the other, terrible as it seemed
让我去偷丈夫的
to take my husband's paper,
的政治文件
in a matter of politics
政治方面我反正不懂
I could not understand it.
而爱和信任的重要性
While in the matter of love and trust
我是十分理解的
it was only too clear to me.
是我干的 福尔摩斯先生
I did it, Mr. Holmes.
是我干的
I did it.
我编造了去剧院的故事
I invented a story about going to the theatre.
第二天早晨
The next morning
我发现我只是用新麻烦
I realized I'd only exchanged
代替了旧烦恼
one trouble for another.
我跟踪丈夫来到贝克街
I followed my husband to Baker Street
然后一个人来见你
and then came to you myself
为了弄明白
in order to understand
这件事的后果
the full enormity of the offence.
我是唯一知道
I alone in the world
文件下落的人
knew where the paper was hidden.
我只有一个想法
My whole mind was turned to the one thought
就是把它拿回来
of getting it back.
我所做的
What I did,
他回来了
here he is now.
有什么消息 福尔摩斯先生
Any news Mr. Holmes?
有什么消息
Any news?
有希望了
I have some hopes.
这事事关政治 亲爱的
This is a matter of politics, my dear.
时间不会太长
We shall not be long.
首相和我们一起用午餐
The Prime Minister is lunching with us.
他可以来听听吧
May he share your hopes.
他意志刚强 据我所知
He has nerves of steel and yet I know
他自从这件可怕的事发生后
that he's hardly slept
几乎没睡过觉
since this terrible event.
福尔摩斯有些事要告诉我们 先生
Mr. Holmes has some news for us, sir.
你有什么好消息 福尔摩斯先生
What have you to report, Mr. Holmes?
目前还没有弄清
Purely negative as yet.
我都调查过了
I have made inquiries
对于任何有可能的地方
at every point where it might be,
我敢肯定不必担心
and I'm sure there's no danger
有危险
to be apprehended.
这可不够 福尔摩斯先生
That's not enough, Mr. Holmes.
我们不能永远活在火山顶上
We cannot live on this volcano.
我们要把事情弄清楚
We must have something definite.
我觉得找到信还是很有希望的
I have high hopes of getting the letters back.
这就是我在这里的原因
That is why I'm here.
我越想
The more I think of it
越觉得
the more I am convinced
这封信根本没离开过您家
that the letter has never left this house.
真的吗 福尔摩斯先生
Oh really, Mr. Holmes.
可是为什么会有人拿走文件
But why should anybody take it in order
只是为了藏在家里?
to keep it in this house?
我不觉得有人拿走了它
I'm not convinced that anybody has taken it.
福尔摩斯先生 这个玩笑可不合时宜
Mr. Holmes, this joking is very ill timed.
我可以肯定有人拿了
You have my assurance it was taken.
你从上个周二起
Have you examined the box carefully
仔细地检查过箱子吗
since last Tuesday morning?
没有
No not thoroughly.
我觉得没有必要
I did not consider it necessary.
你很可能
You could conceivably
没看到那封信
have overlooked the letter.
这不可能 先生
That is impossible, sir.
这种事我见多了
I have known such things happening.
你的箱子里还有别的文件吗
You have other papers in the box?
是的 所有我的私密文件
Yes, all my confidential papers.
可能和别的浑在一起了
It could have got mixed with them.
那封信在最顶上
It was on the top.
箱子可能被摇晃过
The box could have been shaken.
我都摆好的
I had everything out.
很容易整理的
It's easily settled.
咱们去看看吧
Let's go and look.
这绝对是在浪费时间
This is a farcical waste of time,
不过
but still,
如果没有什么别的事能让你满意
if nothing else will satisfy you,
就去看看吧
it shall be done.
这都是我的私密文件
Here are all my confidential papers
如你所见
as you can see.
这是梅罗爵士的信
It's a letter from Lord Merrow,
查理斯・哈迪伯爵的报告
report from Sir Charles Hardy,
贝尔格雷地的备忘录 这是
memorandum from Belgrade, that's the one
我们今早在讨论的文件 首相
we were discussing this morning, Prime Minister,
俄国和德国的粮食税记录
note on the Russo-German grain taxes,
马德里的来信
letter from Madrid,
弗拉沃爵士的记录
note from Lord Flowers...
是的 就是它
Yes, this is it.
信完好无损
And the letter is intact.
太神奇了
Remarkable.
难以置信
This is inconceivable.
不可能 福尔摩斯
Impossible, Mr. Holmes.
希尔达
Hilda?
你怎么知道它在这儿
How did you know it was here?
因为我知道不在别的地方
Because I knew it was nowhere else.
我不敢相信我的眼睛
I cannot believe my eyes!
希尔达 我们找到信了
Hilda, we have found the letter
我知道
and I know it is difficult
你很难理解这种事
for you to understand
但这是最好的消息
but it is the most wonderful news.
非常不同寻常
It's quite extraordinary.
我把每个文件都翻过了
I went through every paper in here.
我检查又检查
I checked and I rechecked.
不可思议 它就在里面
It's incomprehensible that I should have overlooked it
我竟然没看到它
in this manner.
先生们
Oh gentlemen.
来
Come,
这里面一定有什么秘密
there's more in this than meets the eye.
首相
Prime Minister,
我们也有我们的外交秘密
we too have our diplomatic secrets.
-==www.RagBear.com==-